chapter 4.
On Sunday morning while church bells rang in the villages along Shore the
world and its mistress returned to Gatsby’s house and twinkled hilariously
on his lawn. “He’s a bootlegger,” said the young ladies, moving somewhere between
his cocktails and his flowers.
“One time he killed a man who had found out that he was a nephew to Von
Hindenburg and second cousin to the devil.
Reach me a rose, honey, and pour me a last drop into that there crystal glass.”
Once I wrote down on the empty space of a timetable the names of those who came
to Gatsby’s house that summer. It is an old timetable now, disintegrating at its
folds, and headed “This schedule in effect July 5th, 1922.”
But I can still read the gray names, and they will give you a better impression
than my generalities of those who accepted Gatsby’s hospitality
and paid him the subtle tribute of knowing nothing whatever about him. From
East Egg, then, came the Chester Beckers and the Leeches, and the man named Bunsen,
whom I knew at Yale, and Dr Webster Civet, who was drowned last summer up in Maine.
And the Hornbeams and the Willy Voltaires, and a whole clan named black
Buck who always gathered in a corner and flipped up their noses like goats at
whosoever came near. And the Ismays and the Christies were rather Hubert auberg
and Mr Christie's wife), and Edgar Beaver, whose hair, they say,
turned Cotton white one winter afternoon for no good reason at all.
Clarence Endive was from East Egg, as I remember. He came only once, in white
knickerbockers, and had a fight with a bum named Eddie in the garden. From
further out on the Island came the Cheetos and the orp schraders and the
Stonewall Jackson Abrahams of Georgia, and the fish guards and the Ripley
Snells. Snell was there three days before he went to the penitentiary, so drunk out
on the gravel drive that Mrs. Ulysses sweats automobile ran over his right hand.
The dances came, too an SB white bait who is well over 60 and Maurice A. Flink, and
the Hammerheads, and Beluga the tobacco importer, and Beluga’s girls. From West
Egg came the Poles and the mulridis and Cecil robach and Cecil Sean and gullick
the State senator and Newton Orchid, who controlled Films bar Excellence, and the
exhaust and Clyde Cohen and Don C Schwartz (the Sun and Arthur McCarty, all
connected with the movies in one way or another. And the cat lips and the
benbergs and G. Earl Muldoon, brother to that Muldoon who afterwards strangled his wife
defontano the promoter came there, and Ed legrose and James B rotcut Ferret and
the dejongs and Ernest Lilly— —they came to gamble, and when Ferret wandered into
the garden it meant he was cleaned out an associate attraction would have to
fluctuate profitably next day.
A man named Clip Springer was there so often and so long that he became known
as “the Border I doubt if he had any other home.
Of theatrical people there were guzz ways and Horace O'Donovan and Lester
Meyer and George Duckweed and Francis Bull. Also from New York were the Chromes
and the bakasans and the denikers and Russell Betty and the Corrigans and the
Kellers and the doers and the scullies and and SW Belcher and the smirks and
the young Quinns, divorced now, and Henry ala Palmetto, who killed himself by
jumping in front of a subway train in Times Square. Benny McLean arrived always
with four girls. They were never quite the same ones and physical person, but
they were so identical with another that it inevitably seemed they had been there
before. I had forgotten their names Jacqueline I think, or else Consuela, or
Gloria or Judy or June, and their last names were either the melodious names of
flowers and months or the sterner ones of the great American capitalists whose
cousins, if pressed, they would confess themselves to be. In addition to all
these I can remember that Faustina O’Brien came there at least once and the
bedecker girls and young Brewer, who had his nose shot off in the war, and Mr
albrechtsberger and Miss Hague his fiancee and our deep to fitzpeters and
Mr. P. Jewett one head of the American Legion, and Miss Claudia Hip, with a man
reputed to be her chauffeur, and a prince of something, whom we called Duke, and
whose name, if I ever knew it, I had forgotten.
All these people came to Gatsby’s house in the summer.
At nine o’clock, one morning late in July, Gatsby’s gorgeous car lurched up the
rocky drive to my door and gave out a burst of melody from its three-noted horn.
It was the first time he'd called on me, though I had gone to two of his parties,
mounted in his hydroplane, and, at his urgent invitation, made frequent use of his beach.
“Good morning, old sport.
You’re having lunch with me today and I thought we’d ride up together.”
He was balancing himself on the dashboard of his car with that
resourcefulness of movement that is so peculiarly American— —that comes, I suppose,
with the absence of lifting work or rigid sitting in youth and, even more,
with the formless grace of our nervous, sporadic games.
This quality was continually breaking through his punctilious manner in the
shape of restlessness.
He was never quite still; there was always a tapping foot somewhere or the impatient opening and
closing of a hand.
He saw me looking with admiration at his car.
“It’s pretty, isn’t it, old sport?” He jumped off to give me a better view.
“Haven’t you ever seen it before?” I’d seen it everyone had seen it.
It was a rich cream color bright with nickel, swollen here and there in its
monstrous length with triumphant hat boxes and supper boxes and tool boxes
and terraced with a labyrinth of windshields that mirrored a dozen suns.
Sitting down behind many layers of glass in a sort of green leather conservatory,
we started to town.
I had talked with him perhaps half a dozen times in the past month and found,
to my disappointment, that he had little to say.
So my first impression, that he was a person of some undefined consequence, had
gradually faded and he had become simply the proprietor of an elaborate Road house next door.
And then came that disconcerting ride.
We hadn’t reached West Egg village before Gatsby began leaving his elegant
sentences unfinished and slapping himself indecisively on the knee of his caramel colored suit.
“Look your old sport,” he broke out surprisingly, “what’s your opinion of me,
anyhow?” A little overwhelmed, I began the generalized evasions which that question deserves.
“Well, I’m gonna tell you something about my life,” he interrupted. “I don’t want you
to get a wrong idea of me from all these stories you hear.”
So he was aware of the bizarre accusations that flavored conversations
in his halls. “I’ll tell you God’s truth.” His right hand suddenly ordered divine
retribution to stand by I'm the son of some wealthy people in the Middle West— —all dead now.
I was brought up in America but educated at Oxford, because all my ancestors have
been educated there for many years. It is a family tradition.”
He looked at me sideways— —and I knew why Jordan Baker had believed he was lying.
He hurried the phrase “educated at Oxford,” or swallowed it, or choked on it, as
though it had bothered him before.
And with this doubt, his whole statement fell to pieces, and I wondered if there
wasn’t something a little sinister about him, after all.
“What part of the Middle West?” I inquired casually.
“San Francisco.” “I see.” “My family all died and I came into a good deal of money.”
His voice was solemn, as if the memory of that sudden extinction of a clan still haunted him
my family all died and I came into a good deal of money his voice was solemn
as if the memory of that sudden Extinction of a clan still haunted him
For a moment I suspected that he was pulling my leg, but a glance at him
convinced me otherwise.
“After that I lived like a young Raja on all the capitals of Europe— —Paris, Venice,
Rome— —collecting jewels, chiefly rubies, hunting big game, painting a little,
things for myself only, and trying to forget something very sad that happened to me long ago.”
With an effort I managed to restrain my incredulous laughter. The very phrases
were worn so thread bare that they evoked no image except that of a turbent
character” leaking sawdust at every pores he pursued a tiger through the boy to balloon
Then came the World sport.
It was a great relief, and I tried very hard to die,
but I seemed to bear an enchanted life.
I accepted a commission as first lieutenant when it began. In the Argonne
Forest I took two machine gun detachments so far forward that there
was a half mile gap on either side of us where the infantry couldn’t advance.
We stayed there two days and two nights 130 men with 16 Lewis guns, and when the
infantry came up at last they found the insignia of three German divisions among
the piles of dead.
I was promoted to be a major, and every Allied government gave me a decoration—
—even Montenegro, little Montenegro down on the Adriatic Sea!”
Little Montenegro! He lifted up the words and nodded at them— —with his smile. The
smile comprehended Montenegro’s troubled history and sympathized with the brave
struggles of the Montenegrin people.
It appreciated fully the chain of national circumstances which had
elicited this tribute from Montenegro’s warm little heart.
My incredulity was submerged in fascination now; it was like skimming hastily through a
dozen magazines.
He reached in his pocket, and a piece of metal, slung on a ribbon, fell into my palm.
“That’s the one from Montenegro.” To my astonishment, the thing had an authentic look
ordari di de Neo ran the circular legend, “Montenegro Nicholas Rex.” “Turn it.”
“Major J Gatsby,” I read, “For Valor Extraordinary.” “Here’s another thing I always carry. A
souvenir of Oxford days. It was taken in Trinity Quad—
—the man on my left is now the Earl of Dorchester
It was a photograph of a half a dozen young men in blazers loafing in an
archway through which were visible a host of spiers There was Gatsby, looking a little, not
much, younger— —with a cricket ball in his hand.
Then it was all true.
I saw the skins of tigers flaming in his palace on the Grand Canal; I saw him
opening a chest of rubies to ease, with their Crimson lighted depths, the
gnawings of his broken heart.
“I’m going to make a big request of you today,” he said, pocketing his souvenirs
with satisfaction, “so I thought you ought to know something
about me. I didn’t want you to think I was just some nobody.
You see, I usually find myself among strangers because I drift here and there
trying to forget the sad thing that happened to me.” He hesitated.
“You’ll hear about it this afternoon.” “At lunch?” “No, this afternoon.
I happened to find out that you’re taking Miss Baker to tea.”
“Do you mean you’re in love with Miss Baker?” “No, old sport, I’m not.
But Miss Baker has kindly consented to speak to you about this matter.”
I hadn’t the faintest idea what “this matter” was, but I was more annoyed than
interested. I hadn’t asked Jordan to tea in order to discuss Mr Jake Gatsby. I was
sure the request would be something utterly fantastic, and for a moment I was
sorry I’d ever set foot upon his overpopulated lawn.
He wouldn’t say another word. His correctness grew on him as we neared the city.
We passed Port Roosevelt, where there was a glimpse of red belted ocean-going
ships, and sped along a cobbled slum lined with the dark, undeserted saloons
of the Faded guilt 1900s Then the valley of ashes opened out on
both sides of us, and I had a glimpse of Mrs. Wilson straining at the garage pump
with panting vitality as we went by.
With fenders spread like wings we scattered light through half Long Island
City only half, for as we twisted among the pillars of the elevated I heard the
familiar duck took spot of a motorcycle, and a frantic policeman rode alongside.
“All right, old sport,” called Gatsby. We slowed down.
Taking a white card from his wallet, he waved it before the man’s eyes.
“Right you are,” agreed the policeman, tipping his cap. “Know you next time, Mr.
Gatsby. Excuse me “What was that?” I inquired. “The picture of Oxford?”
“I was able to do the commissioner a favor once, and he sends me a Christmas card every
year.” Over the great bridge, with the sunlight through the girders making a constant
flicker upon the moving cars, with the city rising up across the river in white
heaps and sugar lumps all built with a wish out of non-of-factory money. The
city scene from the Queensborough Bridge is always the city scene for the first
time, in its first wild promise of all the mystery and the beauty in the world.
A dead man passed us in a hearse heaped with blooms, followed by two carriages
withdrawn blinds, and by more cheerful carriages for friends.
The friends looked at us with the tragic eyes and short upper lips of southern Europe,
and I was glad that the site of Gatsby’s splendid car was included in their somber holiday.
As we crossed Blackwell’s Island a limousine past us, driven by a white
chauffeur, in which sat three modest negroes, two bucks and a girl. I laughed
aloud as the Yokes of their eyeballs rolled toward us in haughty rivalry.
“Anything can happen now that we’ve slid over the bridge,” I thought; “anything at all…”
Even Gatsby could happen, without any particular wonder.
Roaring noon. In a well fanned 42nd Street cellar I met Gatsby for lunch.
Blinking away the brightness of the street outside, my eyes picked him out
obscurely in the ante room talking to another man. “Mr Caraway this is my friend
Mr wolfsheim A small, flat-nosed Jew raised his large head and regarded me
with two fine growths of hair which luxuriated in either nostril.
After a moment I discovered his tiny eyes in the half Darkness
So I took one look at him,” said Mr wolfsheim shaking my hand earnestly, “and
what do you think I did?” “What?” I inquired politely. But evidently
he was not addressing me, for he dropped my hand and covered Gatsby with his
expressive nose. “I handed the money to katzpah and I said: ‘All right catspa
don’t pay him a penny till he shuts his mouth.’
He shut it then and there.” Gatsby took an arm of each of us and moved forward into
the restaurant, whereupon Mr wolfsheim swallowed a new sentence he was starting
and lapsed into his somnambulatory abstraction High balls asked the headwaiter This is
a nice restaurant here,” said Mr wolfsheim looking at the presbyterian nymphs on the ceiling.
“But I like across the street better!” “Yes High balls agreed Gatsby, and then to Mr wolfsheim
It’s too hot over there.” “Hot and small— —yes,” said Mr wolfsheim
but full of memories.” “What place is that?” I asked.
“The old Metropole.” “The old Metropole,” brooded Mr wolfsheim gloomily. “Filled
with faces dead and gone.
Filled with faith is gone now forever. I can’t forget so long as I live the night
they shot Rosie Rosenthal there. It was six of us at the table, and Rosie had
eaten drunk a lot all evening.
When it was almost morning the waiter came up to him with a funny look and
says somebody wants to speak to him outside. ‘All right,’ says Rosie and begins
to get up, and I pulled him down in his chair.
‘Let the bastards come in here if they want you Rosie but don’t you, so help me,
move outside this room.’ “It was four o’clock in the morning then,
and if we’d have raised the blinds we’d have seen daylight.”
“Did he go?” I asked innocently. “Sure he went.” Mr wolfsheim's nose flashed at me
indignantly. “He turned around in the door and says: ‘Don’t let the waiter take away my coffee!’
Then he went out on the sidewalk, and they shot him three times in his full
belly and drove away.” “Four of them were electrocuted,” I said,
remembering. “Five, with Becker.” His nostrils turned to me in an interested way.
“I understand you’re looking for a business connection The juxtaposition of these two remarks
was startling.
Gatsby answered for me: “Oh, no,” he exclaimed, “this isn’t the man.”
“No?” Mr wolfsheim seemed disappointed.
“This is just a friend.
I told you we’d talk about that some other time.”
“I beg your pardon,” said Mr wolfsheim I had a wrong man.” A succulent hash arrived, and Mr
wolfsheim for getting the more sentimental atmosphere of the old
Metropole, began to eat with a ferocious delicacy. His eyes, meanwhile robed very
slowly all around the room— —he completed the Ark by turning to
inspect the people directly behind.
I think that, except for my own presence, he would have taken one short glance
beneath our own table. “Look here, old sport,” said Gatsby, leaning toward me,
“I’m afraid I made you a little angry this morning in the car.”
There was the smile again, but this time I held out against it.
“I don’t like mysteries,” I answered, “and I don’t understand why you won’t come out
frankly and tell me what you want.
Why is it all got to come through Miss Baker?” “Oh, it’s nothing underhand,” he assured me.
“Miss Baker’s a great sportswoman, you know, and she’d never do anything that
wasn’t all right.” Suddenly he looked at his watch, jumped
up, and hurried from the room, leaving me with Mr wolfsheim at the table.
“He has to telephone,” said Mr wolfsheim following him with his eyes. “Fine fellow,
isn’t he? Handsome to look at and a perfect gentleman.” “Yes.” “He’s an Oxford man.”
“Oh!” “He went to Oxford College in England.
You know Oxford College?” “I’ve heard of it.” “It’s one of the most
famous colleges in the world.” “Have you known Gatsby for a long time?” I
inquired. “Several years,” he answered in a gratified way. “I made the pleasure of his
acquaintance just after the war. But I knew I had discovered a man of fine
breeding after I talked with him an hour.
I said to myself: ‘There’s the kind of man
you’d like to take home and introduce to your mother and sister.’ He paused.
“I see you’re looking at my cuff buttons.”
I hadn’t been looking at them, but I did now.
They were composed of oddly familiar pieces of ivory.
“Finest specimens of human molars,” he informed me.
“Well!” I inspected them.
“That’s a very interesting idea.” “Yeah.” He flipped his sleeves up under his coat.
“Yeah Gatsby is very careful about women.
He would never so much as look at a friend’s wife.” When the subject of this instinctive
trust returned to the table and sat down Mr wolfsheim drank his coffee with a
jerk and got to his feet.
“I have enjoyed my lunch,” he said I’m going to run off from you two young men
before I outstand my welcome.” “Don’t hurry Meyer,” said Gatsby, without enthusiasm. Mr
wolfsheim raised his hand in a sort of benediction. “You’re very polite, but I
belong to another generation,” he announced solemnly. “You sit here and
discuss your sports and your young ladies and your—” He supplied an imaginary
noun with another wave of his hand. “As
for me, I am 50 years old, and I won’t
impose myself on you any longer.” As you shook hands and turned away his tragic
nose was trembling.
I wondered if I had said anything to offend him. “He becomes very sentimental
sometimes,” explained Gatsby. “This is one of his sentimental days.
He’s quite a character around New York— —a Denison at Broadway.”
“Who is he, anyhow, an actor?” “No.” “A dentist?” “Meyer wolfsheim No, he’s a gambler.”
Gatsby hesitated, then added, coolly: “He’s the man who fixed the World Series back
in 1919.”. “Fixed the World Series?” I repeated. The idea staggered me. I
remembered, of course, that the World Series had been fixed in 1919, but if I
had thought of it at all I would have thought of it as a thing that merely
happened the end of some inevitable chain.
It never occurred to me that one man could start to play with the faith of 50
million people— —with the single-mindedness of a burglar blowing a safe.
“How did he happen to do that?” I asked after a minute. “He just saw the opportunity.”
“Why isn’t he in jail?” “They can’t get him, old sport. He’s a smart man.”
I insisted on paying the check. As the waiter brought my change I caught sight
of Tom Buchanan across the crowded room.
“Come along with me for a minute,” I said; “I’ve got to say hello to someone.”
When he saw us Tom jumped up and took half a dozen steps in our direction
where have you been?” he demanded eagerly. “Daisy’s furious because you haven’t called up.”
“This is Mr. Gatsby, Mr. Buchanan.” They shook hands briefly, and a strained,
unfamiliar look of embarrassment came over Gatsby’s face
have you been, anyhow?” demanded Tom of me.
“How’d you happen to come up this far to eat?”
“I’ve been having lunch with Mr. Gatsby.” I turned toward Mr. Gatsby,
but he was no longer there.
One October day in 1917. said Jordan Baker that afternoon, sitting up very
straight on a straight chair in the Tea Garden at the Plaza Hotel)
—I was walking along from one place to another, half on the sidewalks and half
on the lawns. I was happier in the lawns because I had on shoes from England with
rubber knobs on the soles that bit into the soft ground.
I had on a new plaid skirt also that blew a little in the wind, and whenever
this happened the red, white, and blue banners in front of all the houses
stretched out stiff and said in a disapproving way.
The largest of the banners and the largest of the lawns belonged to Daisy
Faye's house. She was just 18. two years older than me, and by far the most
popular of all the young girls in Louisville.
She dressed in white, and had a little white roadster, and all day long the
telephone rang in her house and excited young officers from Camp Taylor demanded
the privilege of monopolizing her that night. “Anyways, for an hour!”
When I came opposite her house that morning her white roadster was beside
the curb and she was sitting in it with a lieutenant I had never seen before.
They were so engrossed in each other that she didn’t see me until I was five
feet away.
“Hello, Jordan,” she called unexpectedly. “Please come here.”
I was flattered that she wanted to speak to me, because of all the older girls I
admired her the most. She asked me if I was going to the Red Cross and make
bandages. I was. Well, then, would I tell them that she couldn’t come that day?
The officer looked at Daisy while she was speaking, in a way that every young
girl wants to be looked at sometime, and because it seemed romantic to me I
remembered the incident ever since. His name was Jay Gatsby,
and I didn’t lay eyes on him again for
over four years— —even after I’d met him on Long Island I didn’t realize it was
the same man.
That was 1917. By the next year I had a
few Beau myself, and I began to play in tournaments, so I didn’t see Daisy very
often. She went with a slightly older crowd— —when she went with anyone at all
rumors were circulating about her— —how her mother had found her packing her bag
one winter night to go to New York and say goodbye to a soldier who was going overseas.
She was effectually prevented, but she wasn’t on speaking terms with her family
for several weeks.
After that she didn’t play around with the soldiers anymore but only with a few
flat-footed short-sighted young men in town, who couldn’t get into the army at all.
By the next autumn she was gay again, gay as ever.
She had a debut after the armistice, and in February she was presumably engaged
to a man from New Orleans. In June she married Tom Buchanan of Chicago, with
more pomp and circumstance than Louisville had ever known before
she came down with a hundred people in four private cars, and hired a whole
floor of the sealbach Hotel, and the day before the wedding he gave
her a string of pearls valued at three hundred and fifty thousand dollars.
I was a bridesmaid. I came into a room half an hour before the bridal dinner,
and found her lying on her bed as lovely as the June night in her flower dress—
—and as drunk as a monkey. She had a bottle of salt turn in one hand and a
letter in the other congratulate me,” she muttered. “Never had a
drink before, but oh how I do enjoy it it's the matter, Daisy?”
I was scared, I can tell you; I’d never seen a girl like that before.
“Here dears She groped around in a waste basket she had with her on the bed and
pulled out the string of pearls. “Take them downstairs and come back to whoever
they belong to. Tell him daisies change your mind Say daisies change your mind She began to cry—
—she cried and cried. I rushed out and found her mother’s maid, and we locked
the door and got her into a cold bath.
She wouldn’t let go of the letter.
She took it into the tub with her and squeezed it up into a wet ball, and only
let me leave it in the soap dish when she saw that it was coming to pieces
like snow.
But she didn’t say another word.
We gave her spirits of ammonia and put ice on her forehead and hooked her back
into her dress, and half an hour later we walked out of the room,
the pearls were around her neck and the incident was over.
Next day at five o’clock she married Tom Buchanan without so much as a shiver, and
started off on a three-month trip to the South Seas.
I saw them in Santa Barbara when they came back, and I thought I’d never seen a
girl so mad about her husband. If he left the room for a minute she’d look around
uneasily, and say: “Where’s Tom gone?” and where the most abstracted expression
until she saw him coming in the door.
She used to sit on the sand with his head in her lap by the hour, rubbing her
fingers over his eyes and looking at him with unfathomable delight.
It was touching to see them together— —it made you laugh in a hushed, fascinated way.
That was in August.
A week after I left Santa Barbara Tom ran into a wagon on the Ventura road one
night, and ripped a front wheel off his car.
The girl who was with him got into the papers, too, because her arm was broken—
—she was one of the chamber maids in the Santa Barbara Hotel.
The next April Daisy had her little girl, and they went to France for a year.
I saw them on spring in canes and later in doauville and then they came back to
Chicago to settle down.
Daisy was popular in Chicago, as you know.
They moved with a fast crowd, all of them young and rich and wild, but she came out
with an absolutely perfect reputation.
Perhaps because she doesn’t drink.
It’s a great advantage not to drink among hard drinking people. You can hold
your tongue and, moreover, you can time any little irregularity of your own so
that everybody else is so blind that they don’t see or care.
Perhaps Daisy never went in for a more at all— —and yet there’s something in that voice
of hers… Well, about six weeks ago, she heard the name Gatsby for the first time in years.
It was when I asked you— —do you remember?— ?—if you knew Gatsby in West Egg.
After you had gone home she came into my room and woke me up, and said: “What Gatsby?”
and when I described him— —I was half asleep— —she said in the strangest voice that it
must be the man she used to know. It wasn’t until then that I connected this
Gatsby with the officer in her white car.
When Jordan Baker had finished telling all this we had left the Plaza for half
an hour and were driving in the victoria through Central Park.
The sun had gone down behind the tall apartments of the movie stars in the
West 50s and the clear voices of girls already gathered like crickets in the
grass, rose through the hot twilight: “I’m the Sheik of arabay Your love belongs to me.
At night when you’re asleep Into your tent I’ll creep—”
“It was a strange coincidence,” I said.
“But it wasn’t a coincidence at all.” “Why not?” “Gatsby bought that house so that Daisy
would be just across the bay.” Then it had not been merely the stars to
which he had aspired on that June night.
He came alive to me, delivered suddenly from the womb of his purposeless splendor
He wants to know,” continued Jordan, “if you’ll invite Daisy to your house some afternoon
and then let him come over.” The modesty of the demand shook me.
He had waited five years and bought a mansion where he dispensed starlight to
casual moths— —so that he could “come over” some afternoon to a stranger’s garden.
“Did I have to know all this before he could ask such a little thing?”
“He’s afraid, he’s waited so long. He thought you might be offended.
You see, he’s a regular tough underneath it all.” Something worried me.
“Why didn’t he ask you to arrange a meeting?” “He wants her to see his house,” she
explained. “And your house is right next door.” “Oh!” “I think he half expected her to wander
into one of his parties, some night,” went on Jordan, “but she never did.
Then he began asking people casually if they knew her, and I was the first one he found.
It was that night he sent for me at his dance, and you should have heard the
elaborate way he worked up to it.
Of course, I immediately suggested a luncheon in New York— —and I thought he’d
go mad: ‘I don’t want to do anything out
of the way!’ he kept saying. ‘I want to see her right next door.’
“When I said you were a particular friend of TOMS he started to abandon the whole idea.
He doesn’t know very much about Tom, though he says he’s read a Chicago paper
for years just on the chance of catching a glimpse of Daisy’s name.” It was dark now,
and as we dipped under a little bridge I put my arm around Jordan’s golden
shoulder and drew her toward me and asked her to dinner.
Suddenly I wasn’t thinking of Daisy and Gatsby anymore but of this clean, hard, limited person,
who dealt in universal skepticism and who leaned back jauntily just within the circle of my arm.
A phrase began to beat in my ears with a sort of heady excitement:
“There are only the pursued, the pursuing, the busy, and the tired.”
“And Daisy ought to have something in her life,” murmured Jordan to me.
“Does she want to see Gatsby?” “She’s not supposed to know about it.
Gatsby doesn’t want her to know. You’re just supposed to invite her to tea.”
We passed a barrier of dark trees, and then the facade of 59th Street, a block
of delicate pale light, beamed down into the park.
Unlike Gatsby and Tom Buchanan, I had no girl whose disembodied face floated
along the dark cornices and blinding signs, and so I drew up the girl beside
me, tightening my arms. Her wands scornful mouth smiled, and so I drew her up again closer,
this time to my face